{"tossups": [{"question": "<b>In the 12th century, a man from this city named Margaritus became the first count of Malta. Marcus Pacuvius was a 2nd century BC poet from this city, where Virgil died in</b> <b>19 BC. After fleeing from Caesar\u2019s forces to this city, (+)</b> <b>Pompey took a ship to Epirus.</b> <b>Located in the region of Apulia, this city once contained two \u201cterminal columns\u201d that marked the (*) </b> end of a route whose construction began during the Samnite Wars. The Greek for\u201cDeer\u2019s head\u201d is the etymology of the name of, for the points, what Italian coastal city connected to Rome via the Appian Way?", "answer": "<b> Brindisi</b> (accept<b> Brundisium</b>; accept<b> Brinnisi</b>)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>Some modified Corinthian capitals at this city are shaped like elephants and winged cats. A theater in this city includes statues of Heracles and Aphrodite. A building located above</b> <b>(+)</b> <b>al-Siq at this site has a facade that includes a broken pediment as well as depictions</b> <b>of Isis-Tyche, as well as Castor and Pollux; that building, a tomb for King (*)</b> Aretas IV in this city, is more commonly known as the Treasury, or the Khazneh. For the points, name this Nabataean capital, a city carved out of rock in modern Jordan.", "answer": "<b> Petra</b>", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "<b>Members of this group are thought to be behind the killing of the undersheriff Osman Steele. Handbills sent out by members of this group called for people to \u201cAwake! Arouse!\u201d</b> <b>A doctor and leading member of this group went by the name Big Thunder. (+)</b> <b>Smith</b> <b>Boughton, another leader of this group, was prosecuted by state attorney general John van Buren after these people rioted against the patroonship system that had allowed for the vastness of (*)</b> Stephen Van Rensselaer III\u2019s estate. Governor Silas Wright lost his re-election campaign in 1846 after calling the military against, for the points, what group in upstate New York in the 1840s that revolted against about the back collection of their tenant debts?", "answer": "<b> Anti-Rent</b> Party (accept<b> Anti-Renter</b>s; accept<b> Anti-Rent</b> Movement; accept<b> Anti-Rent </b>War)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>A Frenchman named Choqueux [sho-koh] was a suspect in this event until it was revealed that he made fireworks for a living. In the midst of this event, a man was found dead at Primrose Hill with apparent stab wounds; (+) Miles Prance was accused of that murder of Sir Edmund Godfrey. William Bedloe served as a prosecutor in thiss event, whose planner was assisted by Israel Tongue and had attended a (*)</b> Jesuit school in Omer. Roughly two dozen men were executed as a result of, for the points, what conspiracy theory, devised by Titus Oates, that claimed Charles II\u2019s life was in grave Catholic danger?", "answer": "<b> Popish</b> Plot", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>In 1681, the people of this colony organized an unsuccessful \u201cday of fasting and public prayer\u201d after they thought that their leader had fallen ill due to a recent comet sighting; though John Cutt died, this state continued to observe Fast Day until 1991. Elizabeth Hanson, a resident of this colony, wrote a captivity narrative after being abducted during</b> <b>(+)</b> <b>Father Rale\u2019s War. Samuel Allen was the first governor of this colony, from which</b> <b>Benning Wentworth issued over one hundred land grants. The overlap between this colony\u2019s grants and those issued by (*)</b> New York ultimately led to the creation of Vermont. For the points, name this American colony with capital at Concord.", "answer": "Province of<b> New Hampshire</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>This position was controlled by the Main Political Directorate and was weakened by the Frunze Reforms of the 1920s. Holders of this position often clashed with the military over the idea of</b><em><b> edinonachalie</b></em><b>, or (+) unified command, as they both held authority over units; in practice, some military commanders adopted this position. The German OKW issued an order immediately before Operation (*) </b> Barbarossa ordering the execution of holders of this position. Nikita Khrushchev held this position during the Siege of Stalingrad. For the points, give this term for political officers that suppressed dissent and ensured civilian control of the Soviet army.", "answer": "Political<b> commissar</b> (or<b> zampolit</b> or<b> politruk</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>The tutor William Henry Donald was sent to negotiate an end to this event, in which propaganda minister Shao Yuanchong was killed while climbing a fence. The Blue Shirts Society attempted to convince (+) He Yingqin to intervene militarily in this event, though it was eventually resolved by a delegation led by Zhou Enlai. Yang Hucheng was executed 13 years after his involvement in this event, which led to a (*) </b> United Front between the Communists and the Kuomintang against Japan. For the points, name this December 1936 event in which Zhang Xueliang arrested and essentially kidnapped Chiang Kai-Shek.", "answer": "<b> Xi\u2019an Incident</b> (prompt on descriptions of the kidnapping of Chiang Kai-Shek before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b>This man used his elite musketeers, the Jazayerchi, to capture Sa\u2019adat Khan during an ambush at Kanjpura in his most famous battle. This ruler came to power at the Moghan Plain, where government officials appointed him king over (+) Abbas III, even though this man had earlier destroyed the Hotaki dynasty to restore Tahmasp II to the throne. This man was victorious at the Battle of (*)</b> Karnal, after which he captured the Peacock Throne of the Mughal Empire. For the points, name this Afsharid Shah of Iran who took power from the Safavids and sacked Delhi in 1731.", "answer": "<b> Nader</b> Shah (or<b> Nader</b> Qoli Beyg)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b>This author wrote the lines \u201cI thought: it\u2019s impossible to love a loose woman / As if she were a bride\u201d in a poem addressed one of many lovers that she acquired at The Stray Dog restaurant. This writer declared \u201cgravestones are fragile / and granite is softer than wax\u201d in a poem that calls her (+) Prince Charming a \u201cprince of the mockers.\u201d A poem by</b> <b>this woman was inspired by waiting for (*)</b> seventeen months to visit her son in prison, and she suffered the execution of her first husband and imprisonment of her third in a gulag. For the points, name this Russian author of \u201cPoem without a Hero\u201d and \u201cRequiem.\u201d", "answer": "Anna<b> Akhmatova</b>", "metadata": "Literature - European Literature - Poetry"}, {"question": "<b>When news of this event broke, Stephen Crowley and Bryan Ellis were killed by angry students who burned the American embassy in Islamabad to the ground. One side in this event first had to gain a</b><em><b> fatwa</b></em><b> from the</b><em><b> ulama</b></em><b> Abdul Aziz bin Baz. According to Lawrence Wright, Christian Proteau\u2019s GIGN forces (+) converted to Islam before they were allowed into action alongside Pakistani commandos in this event. This event was carried out by (*) </b>Abdullah al Qahtani and his al-Ikhwan militia, who declared al Qahtani to be the Mahdi. For the points, name this 1979 event in which hundreds of insurgents took hostages at Islam\u2019s holiest site in Mecca.", "answer": "<b> siege of the Grand Mosque</b> of Mecca (or<b> siege of the Great Mosque</b> of Mecca; accept", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b>This man may have died from infection from the horsehair used in his car seats; this came after he was struck by grenade shrapnel, but was able to leave his vehicle and chase</b> <b>down his assailants with a (+)</b> <b>Luger. This man\u2019s death, which prompted a devastatingly</b> <b>punitive raid on the village of Lidice [lih-dee-tzah], was the goal of Operation (*)</b> Anthropoid, carried out by Jozef Gabcik and Jan Kubis; this \u201cman with an iron heart\u201d died a week after that attack in Prague. For the points, name this head of the SD, a Nazi intelligence group, who helped organize Kristallnacht and the Holocaust.", "answer": "Reinhard<b> Heydrich</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>Description acceptable. In explaining why this action was being taken, its undertaker claimed that he had \u201cno patience with stubborn insistence on private advantage.\u201d This action was taken to prevent a \u201cdangerous intrusion of free speech\u201d in the form of amendments</b> <b>to the (+)</b> <b>Wagner Act. This action sought to protect the right to closed shops, even</b> <b>though its undertaker opposed the recent wave of strikes. This move against a so-called (*)</b>\u201cslave-labor bill\u201d was easily overridden in June 1947. For the points, name this action, a political defeat for Harry Truman, who failed to stop Congress\u2019 weakening of labor unions.", "answer": "Harry S. Truman\u2019s<b> veto</b> of the<b> Taft-Hartley</b> Act (accept<b> Labor Management Relations Act</b> of 1947 in place of<b> Taft-Hartley</b> Act; prompt on partial answers)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>A campaign by this organization placed mailbox bombs in the Westmount neighborhood. A flag used by this organization features a red star on a white background on the left</b> <b>side and solid dark blue on the right. The (+)</b> <b>South Shore Gang was a subgroup of this</b> <b>organization, members of which kidnapped James (*)</b> Cross and Pierre Laporte in an action that prompted Pierre Trudeau to invoke the War Measures Act. For the points, name this Quebec nationalist group that instigated the October Crisis.", "answer": "<b> FLQ</b> (or<b> Front de Liberation de Quebec</b>; accept<b> Quebec Liberation Front</b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b>To allow for this construction project, Richard Nixon signed a nearly one billion dollar Native Claims Settlement Act. The Dalton Highway was built to facilitate this project,</b> <b>which includes underground heat vents to avoid ground (+)</b> <b>melting. This system funds</b> <b>a program created in a 1976 state constitutional amendment that disperses its revenues to citizens via the Permanent (*) </b> Fund Dividend. One section of this system rests on sliders to withstand earthquakes in the Denali Fault, and it makes use of twelve pumping stations between Prudhoe Bay and Valdez. For the points, name this 800-mile petroleum transportation system that spans the largest U.S. state.", "answer": "<b> Trans-Alaska Pipeline</b> System", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "<b>This man was targeted by the Plot of Gorunia, whose planners wished to establish closer relations with Mao Zedong. Though this man shared power early on with Anton Yugov,</b> <b>he usurped power from the (+)</b> <b>Agrarian National Union with a namesake constitution</b> <b>of 1971. This man, who lost support after he attempted to force all Turkish residents to (*)</b> change their names, ordered the Committee for State Security to assassinate Georgi Markov with a ricin-tipped umbrella in London. Petar Mladenov replaced this man just two months before Communism fell in his capital, Sofia. For the points, name this Communist leader who ruled Bulgaria for nearly forty years.", "answer": "Todor<b> Zhivkov</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>An expedition led by this man dislodged natives from the Canyon de Chelly. This man led a group of vigilantes in pursuit of the kidnappers of Ann White, who was eventually killed by her captors as he closed in. This man, who got his start in the party of Jim (+) Bridger, guided John Fremont on his three expeditions to the west and was tasked by the government with forcing the Apache and the Navajo into reservations. This rebel against the (*)</b> Mexicans in California led a New Mexican regiment during the Civil War. For the points, identify this legendary mountain man for whom the capital of Nevada is named.", "answer": "Kit<b> Carson</b> (accept<b> Carson</b> City)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>In the early 1960\u2019s, American Green Berets trained soldiers that formed this country\u2019s Mano Blanca death squads. When a group of leftist peasants occupied the Spanish embassy</b> <b>in this country in 1980, the government intervened and (+)</b> <b>burned the building to the</b> <b>ground. The Victoria 82 campaign targeted revolutionaries in this country and was launched by Efrain (*) </b> Rios Montt. Rigoberta Menchu is an activist for native peoples in, for the points, what Central American country where a four-decade long civil war ended with a 1996 peace agreement, signed in its namesake capital city?", "answer": "<b> Guatemala</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b>After recovering from cancer, this scientist published an article in Discover titled \u201cThe Median Isn\u2019t the Message,\u201d an inspiration to many cancer patients. This scientist wrote a 1981 book about the history of intelligence, to which he later included a forward criticizing (+)</b><em><b> The Bell Curve</b></em><b>. This author of \u201cThe Mismeasure of Man\u201d and \u201cThe Panda\u2019s Thumb\u201d</b> <b>worked with a (*)</b> paleontologist from Columbia to developed a theory of evolution characterized by rapid changes followed by periods of stability. For the points, name this paleontologist who, along with Niles Eldredge, proposed the theory of punctuated equilibrium.", "answer": "Stephen Jay<b> Gould</b>", "metadata": "Social Science - Social Science - Other Social Science"}, {"question": "<b>This man initially worked with his brother Henry in a butcher\u2019s shop before entering his most famous business. After the</b><em><b> Empress of China</b></em><b> left on her maiden voyage, this man</b> <b>expanded his business to Canton. This husband of (+)</b> <b>Sarah Todd funded an expedition</b> <b>that led to the discovery of South Pass and the establishment of a namesake fort along the (*)</b> Columbia. Employees of his most famous company would meet at rendezvous and traveled extensively through the Great Plains. For the points, name this 19th century businessman who established the American Fur Company.", "answer": "John Jacob<b> Astor</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>One of this composer\u2019s operas, featuring a ballet where roller skates were used to depict ice skating, was based on the Anabaptist rebellion in Munster led by John of Leyden. Felix</b> <b>Mendelssohn and this composer were the (+)</b> <b>targets of Richard Wagner\u2019s anti-Semitic</b> <b>tract \u201cOn Jewishness in Music.\u201d The final opera by this composer of</b><em><b> Le proph`ete</b></em><b> was a fictionalized depiction of (*)</b> Vasco da Gama. Valentine loves the Protestant Raoul in another opera by this composer that ends with the St. Bartholomew\u2019s Day Massacre. For the points, name this composer of \u201cgrand operas\u201d such as<em> L\u2019Africaine</em> and<em> Les Huguenots</em>.", "answer": "Giacomo<b> Meyerbeer</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Opera"}, {"question": "<b>A speech commemorating this event borrowed the quote \u201cAnd I shall have some peace there, for peace comes dropping slow\u201d from the grave of a poet who is buried nearby. Timothy Knatchbull and Paul Maxwell were killed in this event, which occurred the same</b> <b>day as the (+)</b> <b>Warrenpoint Ambush. Thomas McMahon was convicted for his role in</b> <b>Warrenpoint Ambush. Thomas McMahon was convicted for his role in</b> <b>this event, which had been attempted a year prior via (*)</b> <b>this event, which had been attempted a year prior via (*)</b> sniper and was carried out via a radio-controlled bomb in Donegal Bay. For the points, name this August 1979 event in which the last British Viceroy of India was killed by the IRA.", "answer": "<b> assassination</b> (or<b> murder</b>,<b> death</b>, etc.) of Louis (Francis Albert Victor Nicholas) <b>Mountbatten</b>, First Earl Mountbatten of Burma (prompt on partial answers) (24) <b>Rock climbers visit this archipelago to climb a 450-foot-tall red sandstone sea stack</b> <b>called the Old Man of Hoy. The St. Magnus Cathedral is found in the town of Kirkwell, which is the largest settlement on these islands. The Churchill Barriers are a set of causeways that connect these islands, which include (+) Burray and Mainland surrounding a body of water called the Scapa Flow, which is home to a naval base. The Pentland Firth separates these islands from the rest of (*) </b> Great Britain, and they lie to the southwest of the more barren Shetland Islands. For the points, name this archipelago off the northeastern coast of Scotland. ANSWER:<b> Orkney</b> Islands", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>In a novel, people working on this project are painted by a watercolor artist nicknamed Rabbit and are treated by the doctor Dorrigo Evans. Colonel Saito is tasked with the</b> <b>construction of a portion of this project in a novel in which Colonel (+)</b> <b>Nicholson refuses</b> <b>to work on it because he is an officer. Labor conditions on this project are central to Richard Flanagan\u2019s novel (*)</b><em> Narrow Road to the Deep North</em> and to a novel by Pierre Boulle. For the points, name this project that included<em> The Bridge over the River Kwai</em> and which brutally employed captured British POWs during World War II.", "answer": "<b> Burma Railway</b> (accept synonyms, like<b> Burma Railroad</b>; prompt on partial answers; prompt on Bridge Over the River Kwai before mentioned; do not accept or prompt on Burma Road) (26) <b>This state was targeted by Kaloyan, who managed to capture its first ruler. It made</b> <b>peace with Theodore I Laskaris with the Treaty of Nymphaion. While waiting for Robert of Courtenay to become ruler, this state was ruled by the regent (+) Yolanda of Flanders. Baldwin IX was crowned the first ruler of this state, which was destroyed by the Empire of (*)</b> Nicaea, led by Michael VIII Palaiologos, thus restoring Byzantine rule. For the points, name this brief empire centered around Constantinople after the Fourth Crusade. ANSWER:<b> Latin</b> Empire (of Constantinople) (do not accept Latin League or other terms)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>This thinker wrote that government structures are put at risk thanks to nature-altering biotechnology in</b><em><b> Our Posthuman Future</b></em><b>. In</b><em><b> America at the Crossroads</b></em><b>, this thinker discussed his support for the Bush administration. Huntington\u2019s (+) Clash of Civilizations hypothesis responded to this thinker\u2019s 1992 work, which noted that the spread of capitalism after the (*)</b> Cold War helped shift societies to the final form of government, liberal democracy. For the points, name this Japanese-American political scientist, the author of<em> The End of History and the Last</em> <em>Man</em>.", "answer": "Francis<b> Fukuyama</b>", "metadata": "Social Science - Social Science - Other Social Science"}, {"question": "<b>This man\u2019s wife, Hannah Wilkinson, is thought to have been the first American women granted a patent. As a youth, this man worked for Jedediah Strutt, who used a technology created by Richard (+) Arkwright. This man employed a village-like management strategy, known as the Rhode Island System, that relied heavily on the (*)</b> labor of women and children and utilized many textile factory techniques that he cleverly memorized while working in England, which forbade their export. For the points, name this \u201cFather of the American Industrial Revolution.\u201d", "answer": "Samuel<b> Slater</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>To put down this effort, colonial forces established a screening and deportation camp at Langata, clearing out the entire native population from the capital. In the early stages</b> <b>of this effort, the assassination of Waruhiu allowed (+)</b> <b>Evelyn Baring to declare a State</b> <b>of Emergency, which included mass arrests in Operation Jock Scott. The arrested included (*)</b> Bildad Kaggia and the other members of the Kapenguria Six, who were accused of drinking human blood in a ritual oath. This effort essentially ended after Dedan Kimathi was captured and killed. For the points, name this 1950s-era, Kikuyu-led revolt against the British in Kenya.", "answer": "<b> Mau Mau</b> Rebellion (or Uprising, Revolt, etc.)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>A tyrant of this city named Aristagoras unsuccessfully tried to capture Naxos for the Persians, after which he led the Ionian revolt, resulting in this city\u2019s destruction by the Persians. A woman from this city was said to have convinced (+) Athens to intervene on its behalf against Samos in the Samian War by lobbying Pericles; that</b><em><b> hetaera</b></em><b> had (*)</b> Pericles\u2019child after his divorce. A 6th century BC philosopher from this city claimed that the nature of all things was water. For the points, name this city, home to Aspasia and Thales [thay-leez], an ancient Greek city in Anatolia.", "answer": "<b> Miletus</b>", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>This man argued that \u201cthere is a great [...] battle to be fought against ignorance,\u201d but if people aren\u2019t \u201cdetermined\u201d to use television to teach or inspire, it\u2019s \u201cnothing but wires</b> <b>and lights in a box.\u201d When speaking with Joseph (+)</b> <b>McCarthy, this man declared \u201cwe</b> <b>must not confuse dissent with disloyalty;\u201d that came during a 1954 report on a program this man co-created with (*)</b> Fred Friendly. During the Blitz, he opened broadcasts with the phrase \u201cThis is London.\u201d For the points, name this radio and television personality, the host of<em> See it Now</em>, who ended wartime reports with the phrase \u201cGood night, and good luck.\u201d", "answer": "Edward R.<b> Murrow</b> (or Egbert R. \u201cEd\u201d<b> Murrow</b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>Description acceptable. This speech derides a woman who \u201cbelieves that 12-year-olds should have the right to sue their parents\u201d after glorifying a previous time when the</b> <b>\u201cGipper was at the helm.\u201d This speech laments the promised (+)</b> <b>\u201cunrestricted abortion</b> <b>on demand\u201d that the Democratic ticket would provide and frames the upcoming election of (*)</b> 1992 as part of an attempt to win \u201cthe soul of America.\u201d For the points, name this speech about the clash between traditional and progressive ideals, given at the Republican Nomination Convention in 1992 by Pat Buchanan.", "answer": "Pat Buchanan\u2019s<b> Culture War</b> Speech (accept answers that use the phrase<b> Culture War</b>; accept descriptions of Pat<b> Buchanan\u2019s RNC speech</b> before \u201cPat\u201d is read; prompt on partial answers)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}